Can Count Binface actually win this election? In a
word, yes. In more words, probably not. But we'll
get to that later. For my American viewers, Count
Binface [music] is an intergalactic space warrior
from the Recyclones who has been running in UK
elections for years, and they're up against Nigel
Farage, who is a far-right politician. First
became an MP in the 2024 election. They're now
in the House of Commons, which is akin to the
House of Reps, but they did not disclose a 5
million pound donation made by a crypto bro.
And that was against parliamentary regulations.
And to avoid the scrutiny of going through
the whole investigative process, they quit.
And when you quit your seat as an MP, [music] you
trigger a bi-election to find a replacement. and
Nigel declared themselves running to be their own
replacement. And it seems the calculus here was if
they get voted back in again overwhelmingly after
people knew about the£5 million crypto donations
that he didn't declare, then mandate from the
people and he very much framed this as a people
versus the establishment situation. I thought
about it hard and I've decided today today I
will resign as a member of parliament for Clton on
Sea. No, I've decided that the people of Clapton
should be the judges of my actions. This will be
a people versus the establishment bi-election.
Then in a rare moment of coordinated genius, all
the other parties that are normally battling each
other agreed to a truce and no one else ran a
candidate in the bi-election and the only person
who declared was Count Binface. The major parties
having all decided not to join in Faraj's little
democracy circus to try and avoid scrutiny
were able to get some pretty good licks in.
But one politician intends to spend the summer
avoiding scrutiny, refusing to set out his plans.
So does he not agree that what the country
deserves is a televised debate between Nigel
Farage and Count Binface? [laughter] My advice
advice to everyone is put your vote in the bin.
that I cannot back joke figures with ridiculous
policies, which is why I'm supporting Count
Binface. Now, because there are no other major
parties running, it means Binface is in a weird
position where technically they could get the
votes to win, although it's not going to be easy
because I mean, Nigel Farage is not from Clactton
on sea. He just picked the over 600 constituencies
in the UK, the one where he was most likely to
get voted in and he got 46.2% 2% of the votes
in the previous election, which means the other
parties got 53.8% of the vote and none of them
are running now. So that leaves 53.8% of the
voters looking for someone else to vote for.
And what about the people that didn't vote? There
were 32,287 eligible voters who did not vote
last time. That's 41.3% of the electorate. If they
were included, Farage technically only got 27.1%
of all eligible voters votes and the other parties
get dropped down to 31.6%. So that's that's a big
big slice of the pie available for Count Binface
to consume Farage. Okay, the fact that Binface
can win established, we should take a moment to
think about why we even have satirical novelty
candidates and do we want them? Well, Count
Binface is all about getting more people to engage
with democracy, encouraging people to make their
vote count, which I think is amazing. And I think
absurd candidates play a very important role. When
I was talking about this with uh my mate Terry,
he came up with the rock paper scissors theory of
political parties, the non-transitive approach,
because you've got your populist
candidates and you got like your serious
politicians. And populists will always
beat serious because they can just promise
whatever they think the people want. And so what
are serious going to do? Well, in comes absurd
political parties. Now, serious politics
is always going to beat absurd politics
because it's just ridiculous. But in a
fantastic non-transitive closing of the loop,
absurd candidates beat populist candidates.
It takes someone with a bin on their head
to point out how ridiculous some of their claims
and promises are and reframe the whole thing
in a much less serious tone while still making
some legitimate points. If you got elected, um
do you realize that you would not be able to wear
your current uh facial covering? the the commons
rules which I've got in front of me here are
very very clear and they forbid face coverings.
Well, I mean the commons rules are very clear
about what you can do with donations, but uh that
seems to have got all murky. So uh why can't I
see how the the line can get tested after Binface
announced their candidacy and it was only Farage
versus Binface. Ah so good. Uh a lot of other
novelty candidates got on the bandwagon. I mean,
one novelty raving party filled three candidates.
So, everyone else got in on the joke, which was we
all know just makes jokes funnier and funnier. So,
there are now over 30 other candidates declared
like the length of like the voting bit of paper
has become a meme in its own right. So, now we
need to work out, do more novelty candidates
like split the vote? Will other candidates joining
in the joke take votes away from Count Binface?
I wanted to get a sense for what could happen
here. And it turns out the Houses of Parliament,
the library keeps all the vote totals for every
candidate in every constituency across all
recent elections. So I could get all the data
from the last four elections for every single
constituency in every election. I pulled out all
the novelty candidates. So, I defined them as not
part of a major party and got under 5% vote share.
I'm not going to I'm not going to release my exact
list because people are going to argue about
it. The point is these are all the fringe silly
novelty like not going to win candidates. I then
counted up how many there were per constituency
and for every single election I did a plot of
number of novelty candidates compared to the
total vote share they got across all of them. And
you can see there is an upwards trend. As you have
more novelty candidates in an election, there is
a a slight increase in the total vote share they
get. So more novelty candidates do all bring more
voters to the table. They increase the size of the
pie. That's great. And this is the average across
all four recent elections. And I'm not saying
it's significant, but it does go up. You could
argue that a quadratic line would fit better. H
that's true almost all the time. You've just got
more things you can adjust on a quadratic than a
linear. So, ignore ignore. The point is point is
it goes it goes up. However, for completeness,
I did all the same plots, but this time I looked
at the average vote share per novelty candidate,
and that has a mild downward trend. So,
it turns out more novelty candidates
uh does dilute the share they get each. They are
splitting up the protest or like other vote, but
it's not as bad as you think because they do also
bring some more voters to the table. But overall,
overall, it's mildly bad news. All of that taken
into account, Count Bimface is probably not going
to win, but that's kind of not the point. The
point is to look at the absurdity of populist
politics and get more people engaged in democracy,
which I think we're achieving. And there is still
an outside chance that the people of Clton could
do the funniest thing ever. Now, some of you may
already know this, but I happen to be close
personal friends with a certain intergalactic
space superhero who swoops in at times like
this when there's confusion and sorts it all out
and explains it logically. Yeah. Oh, in fact.
Oh, hang on. Actually, they're ringing me.
Ringing me right now. Greetings, Matt. Yes, it
is. I, Captain Dissolusion, here to save you
from your Earth politicians. The milk snatchers,
the tricky dicks, all of the Yes. Yes. Captain,
sorry. You're talking about who? Binface. Benface.
What? That recyclon always taking up my low Earth
orbit parking space. And of course, he has a pass.
Captain D's got to pay for parking. But let's
give Count Benface a free pass. I'm not going to
call it discrimination, but that is what it is.
Granted, we don't know what he is under there. But
I'll tell you something else, Matt. I don't know
all the rules on Earth, but where I come from,
you got to be born in the galaxy to run for office
in the galaxy. But sure, let's not get into it.
I don't have time to get into it. Goodbye. Bye.
Where? Yeah. Sorry. No. Uh, it is Count
Binface. Uh, as some of you already know,
I I am a member of the Count Binface. Uh,
but Oh, and actually, oh, there it is. Okay,
now we are we're getting a message in from the bin
himself. Yes, it is me, Count Binface, here to say
good statistical work, Matt. It is my official
stance that yes, we can indeed win this election.
Just [clears throat] maybe not numerically, but
there's more ways to win than that. And hopefully
the people of Clton will put their vote in the bin
and give you plenty to count on election night.
Tell Captain Dillusion that anyone can get a
low Earth orbit parking permit if their intern
is able to fill out the application paperwork
correctly. What is it about your planet and red
tape? Unbelievable. Anyway, I'll show my galactic
birth certificate as soon as I'm not under audit.
Till then, peace and love. Binface out. So, as
the election draws close, if you know anyone in
Clactton, please do reach out and ask them very
nicely to do the objectively hilarious thing. I
mean, come face may not win, but we can definitely
send a message. Uh, it's it's so it's so great.
Anyway, uh I'm just very excited to be part of it
and I can't believe I will be in the room as the
votes come in. So, as the official count agent,
I'll be there verifying that votes are legitimate,
and I will be well, what I'll actually be doing
is keeping track of how many votes are coming in.
I'm going to try and make rolling predictions as
the night goes on as to what the final vote count
will be. And I will put some kind of video
out after the election. Maybe main channel,
maybe second channel. Keep an eye out for it.
The important thing is time is moving on. The
the hour is upon us. to do something in politics,
do something hilarious, do something meaningful.